JACK: Torchwood.
Outside the government,
beyond the police.
Fighting for the future
on behalf of the human race.
The 2 1 st century
is when everything changes
and Torchwood is ready.
Nothing so far.
You getting anything on that?
Well, hold on a tick.
Yes, follow me, Gerald.
-Well?
-We're pretty close.
This way.
Shh!
Don't panic.
I thought you were a ghost.
Scared the wits out of me!
Sorry. Thought you'd be used to us
creeping around by now.
Have you seen any recently? Ghosts?
I've seen three today.
It's getting worse.
-Well, you're a very brave girl.
-Thank you, sir.
(HARRIET CLEARS THROAT)
-Where did you see them?
-In the ward.
Mind, half of this lot
see things anyway.
Nerves shot to pieces. Poor chaps.
Soon as they're better,
they'll be sent back to the front.
Field Marshal Haig's order.
"Every position must be held
to the last man.
"Each one of us must fight
on to the end."
Whenever that is.
Gerald.
(CRACKLING)
Come on.
We're right on top of it.
-Hello?
-TOSHIKO: Tell them.
-Tell us what?
-Tell them what to do.
You're the only one who can stop this.
If you don't,
it's the end of everything.
Tommy...
Take me. I'm in there,
in the ward, in 1918.
You have to take me
so I can be here now.
Just take me!
Tommy? I think you'd better
come with us.
-Why?
-Don't worry.
I'm Gerald and this is Harriet.
We'll look after you.
Who are you?
We're Torchwood.
-GWEN: Who is he?
-Thomas Reginald Brockless.
-Tommy.
-Twenty-four years old.
-Sort of.
-Well, he's either 24 or he's not.
-Depends how you work it out.
-All right, when was he born?
1894.
-Owen, you ready?
-Yeah, nearly.
-Is that a dress, Tosh?
-I do believe it is, Owen.
Well, where is he?
JACK: He's been here for 90 years,
longer than any of us.
Any of you.
TOSHIKO: Torchwood have used alien
cryogenics since Victorian times.
They froze Tommy in 1918.
JACK: So he's 24 or 114 years old.
I know which one I'd choose.
We have to wake him up
every 12 months or so.
Well, defrost him, one day only,
then back in the freezer.
-Why?
-Check he still works.
One day we're gonna need him.
Right, everybody ready?
Come on, Tommy.
Charging 200. Clear!
The thing's shorting.
Charging 360. Clear!
(TOMMY GASPING)
Quick, quick, it's all right.
Get off me! Leave me alone!
-Tommy!
-Leave me alone.
Tommy! Tommy, listen to me!
Tommy Brockless!
It's me. Toshiko.
-Toshiko...
-Remember?
-Gets harder every year.
-Good left hook, though.
Do you know where you are?
Torchwood.
That's right.
Is it time again?
Blimey.
How are you feeling?
I could murder a cup of tea.
IANTO: Don't expect the best china.
-I'm starving.
-Visitors only.
Tuck in, there's enough here
to feed an army.
-Nice dress.
-Thank you.
Got your slacks on underneath.
Is it that cold outside?
It's the fashion this year.
1968 they were in miniskirts.
Thought all my Christmases
had come at once.
Shame they haven't made a comeback.
I still don't get it. Why is he here?
Like I said, one day,
we're gonna need him.
And pull to me. Good, seems fine.
I just need to take a few
-blood samples.
-Blood samples.
We wake you up once a year
and stick needles into you.
-It's not fair.
-Once a year for you,
it's every day for me.
-So, while we wait...
-Tommy Reginald Brockless,
born 1894, February 7th,
in Blackley, Manchester.
Private officer
in 10th West Yorkshire Regiment.
Very good.
Only son of Constance May Bassett,
died 1900,
and Thomas Campbell Brockless,
died June1931, aged 57.
Heart attack.
-That's right, isn't it?
-Yes. I'm sorry.
It's all right. I just haven't had
that much time to get used to it.
OWEN: Right, I need to have
a look at this leg.
St Teilo's Hospital, 1918.
There was a time shift.
A fracture in the rift means that
two slices of time
were erupting into each other.
-A slice of 1918 and...?
-A slice of the future.
But we don't know exactly what slice.
It could be tomorrow,
it could be in 100 years' time.
What will happen?
Chunks of 1918
will start to appear at the hospital.
A few at first, then more and more.
When the time shift is complete,
it'll start a chain reaction.
Unless we stop it,
time shifts'll start happening
all over the country,
-then all over the world.
-But how does Tommy fit in?
He helps us stop it somehow.
Torchwood 1918 left us sealed orders.
"Eyes only documents, FAO Torchwood,
commander overseeing case 1918/TB."
Tommy Brockless?
-Okay, it's stuck.
-No, it's locked.
-Okay, where's the key?
-It's a temporal lock
tied in with the rift frequencies
at the hospital.
-Oh.
-As the rift nears completion,
the box will open and we'll find out
exactly what Tommy does.
But why would they keep us
in the dark, Jack?
I guess we'll find that out, too.
Ta-dah!
-Seriously, what do you think?
-You look like a film star.
-Who, Charlie Chaplin?
-Come on.
Jack, have you got any more
of those pretty boys in the freezer?
Hands off, missy. Tosh got there first.
Thanks for holding the fort
while I'm out.
No worries, have fun. Be careful.
-Where are you off?
-Drink, film, maybe a pizza...
-Oh, very nice.
-Very nice. Very nice.
I'll be on the mobile if you need me.
-Have a lovely time.
-Bye.
He's a frozen soldier from 1918.
Nobody's perfect.
TOSHIKO: Slow down. What's the hurry?
TOMMY: I've only got one day,
I want to see everything.
TOSHIKO: Captain Scott. Sailed from here
when he went off to the Antarctic.
1910. I was 16. Papers were full of it.
Took him two years to get there
and then he snuffed it.
So, what've you been up to
since I last saw you?
Oh, this and that. Work mostly.
(TOMMY LAUGHS)
-What?
-I knew you were going to say that.
It's what you always say.
So how's the piano playing going?
That's what you said
last year, remember?
-"I'm going to learn the piano."
-Never got round to it.
-I bet you never learnt Spanish neither.
-I bought a book, though.
Oh, what are you, made of money?
I haven't had time.
You talk about your life
like you've got no control over it.
Well, Torchwood's pretty much 24/7.
Twenty-four hours a day,
seven days a week.
But you weren't conscripted.
I mean, it's your choice, right?
Yeah, I suppose it is.
-He's a bit of all right.
-He's the boss.
-Nothing changes.
-She's all right, too.
Harriet Derbyshire.
Wonder what happened to her.
She died the year after that was taken.
Twenty-six years old.
So young.
They all were.
Nothing changes.
-Where are you going?
-St Teilo's Hospital.
And bloody cheer up, will you?
Good shot!
You're still winning.
It's alljust maths, really.
Angles, velocity...
Give you women the vote,
equal rights, look what happens, eh?
So, uh, you got a boyfriend yet?
-You sound like my mother.
-Ah, so you haven't, then.
You had a girlfriend? In 1918?
Yeah. Ellie.
We courted for two years.
What happened?
I, uh, stopped seeing her
last time I was home on leave.
The war changed me.
I couldn't just carry on like before.
I'm sorry.
Right pair we make.
(BIRDS FLUTTERING)
(LAUGHTER ECHOING)
Hello.
I said hello.
Can you hear me?
Look, can you hear me? If you just...
(SCREAMS)
Hello?
Are you all right, love?
You look as if you've seen a ghost.
-They're knocking down the hospital?
-Yeah, that's what they said.
Could that have triggered
the time shift?
Could have. Maybe all
the psychic trauma and rift energy
charged it up like a battery.
1918, this place was
full of wounded soldiers.
They'd had four years of it.
Passchendaele, the Somme,
a million British soldiers killed
during the Great War.
It was like walking into hell.
Believe me. I was there.
Owen, you got anything?
All quiet here.
Just that little spike from earlier.
Look, this is more Tosh's thing
than mine.
-Should I give her a call?
-Not yet. Just keep watching.
Yes, mate.
Half a bitter, and a vodka
and diet tonic with a slice of lemon,
please.
(NEWSCASTER ON TV TALKING)
TOSHIKO: Iraq.
Seems like there's always
a war somewhere.
-It's not exactly a war.
-Looks like one.
First year they woke me up, 1919,
they told me it was all over.
We won.
"The war to end all wars," they said.
And then three weeks later,
you had the Second World War.
After all that.
Do you never wonder
if we're worth saving?
-The human race?
-Yes, I think we're worth saving.
Wars and all.
What?
I was just thinking,
I'd do anything for you.
Yeah, all you have to do is say,
"Tommy, you're my brave, handsome hero
and I need you."
-Is that all?
-And whatever it is, I'll do it.
I mean it. Anything.
-What is it?
-I don't know. I just felt something.
(RUSTLING)
Jack.
-Jack.
-Shh!
(WHISPERING) Go ahead.
MAN:
NURSE: I bet you say that
to all the girls.
and my brain simply whirls
NURSE: Shh. Matron won't have singing.
You'll get a good telling off
if she hears you.
OWEN: Jack, you see anything?
'Cause I've got
a little mountain range this end.
Yeah. We've got a few ghosts here.
Gwen, you okay? Gwen?
I'm fine.
They're ready for you now.
Hello?
I see you.
Why won't you leave us alone?
You shouldn't be here.
-I don't mean you any harm.
-You shouldn't be here.
-You shouldn't be here!
-I don't mean you any harm.
I'm going to get you!
-Stop, stop now, please. No, Tommy!
-(LAUGHING) It's a fireman's lift.
-No, stop!
-I'm putting you down.
I'm putting you down.
(BOTH LAUGHING)
-What?
-Nothing.
Thanks.
-Thanks?
-It just caught me out.
It doesn't matter.
What?
I know it's silly,
but I'm a bit older than you.
I was born in 1894.
You know what I mean.
So I'm old enough to die for my country
but I'm too young to give you a kiss?
You daft lass.
What goes on in that head of yours?
Thanks.
You're welcome.
I might be young,
but I've seen a fair bit in my time.
So what do you want to do now?
Well, we could go back to mine,
but there's only room for one
and it's bloody freezing.
You want to come back to my place?
I'm hardly rushing you.
You've known me four years.
Four days.
Okay. Let's go.
I'll race you. Come on.
(MOBILE PHONE RINGING)
Jack.
Toshiko.
We're on our way.
Demolishing the hospital
is what triggers the time shift.
-So, don't demolish it.
-Too late, it's already started.
What happens next?
Two different times
should never exist simultaneously.
You want to be in 1918 or now. Not both.
-So when 1918 becomes fully manifest...
-It's really going to screw us up.
Okay.
Linear time.
Screwed up time.
Imagine your life as a straight line,
from birth to death.
Now try drawing that line on the paper
without straightening it out.
It's impossible.
That's why we've got to stop it.
-Ianto, is that box doing anything yet?
-Still locked.
Okay, we need to find out
how fast the time shift is happening,
get some idea when it's gonna complete.
Tosh, Owen, go to the hospital,
we need readings.
Cover the place with rift monitors.
Gwen, go through the files,
see if there's anything we missed.
-Need a hand?
-Just a couple more.
Listen, Tosh, I've been meaning to say
just be careful.
What do you mean?
You're very close to Tommy.
-I've only known him for four days.
-Yeah.
You've fallen for him, haven't you?
I can be myself with him.
I don't have to pretend.
No, I understand. I didn't think you had
some weird fetish for defrosted men.
I just, um,
don't want you to get hurt. That's all.
If you have to say goodbye.
-GWEN: Owen, can you hear me?
-What is it?
I need you to go down
into the East Wing of the hospital.
Head for the second floor,
what used to be the radiology section.
I think that area contains
a clue to the time shift.
I read this earlier,
but it didn't make any sense.
In the Torchwood 1918 field report
of the hospital
they describe a certain detail
of their encounter.
It reads,
"Through a hole in the external wall,
we hear the roar of great engines.
"Outside is a woman in strange armour,
"ripping a Union Jack, perhaps
some future heroine of the Empire."
I mean, what does it mean?
It doesn't sound like us now. I mean...
The time shift has started,
but maybe it doesn't complete
until years in the future.
Got it!
It's some kind of advert.
It's for car insurance.
The sound they heard
must have been traffic.
It's not years in the future, it's now.
(RAPID BEEPING)
(ALARM BLARING)
Instructions?
Yeah, for Tommy.
And Toshiko.
In 12 hours, there'll be
a brief moment when both times exist,
before the time shift completes,
when Tommy can be here now
and in 1918.
He needs to be in the hospital
ready to step from one time to another.
So he'd be right inside the time shift?
And he can close
the fracture that caused it.
-And when the fracture's closed?
-1918 will be back where it belongs.
So will I.
For good?
Yeah.
You're the only one who can do this.
We brought you from 1918 to now,
and when you go back to 1918,
your life will be like a thread,
stitching time back together again.
A stitch in time.
How?
This is a rift manipulator.
It's basically a key.
Once you're inside the time shift,
you can close the door behind you.
And that's it? I'm gone?
Tommy, stay with Ianto. Tosh, with me.
TOSHIKO: What happens to him?
Three weeks
after we send Tommy back, he dies.
-How?
-He's shot by a firing squad.
I don't understand.
In 1918, Tommy was
suffering from shellshock.
That's why he was in the hospital.
When Torchwood took him and froze him,
they froze his most recent memories.
When he returns to 1918,
he'll revert back to who he was.
He'll be shellshocked
and so he'll be executed
by the British army for cowardice.
They can't shoot him for that.
Lots of soldiers who were
shellshocked recovered enough
to be sent back to the front.
But once they were there,
they broke down again.
-So they kill him?
-More than 300 of them.
-Then we can't send him back.
-We have to.
-I can't do that.
-Yes, you can.
-He trusts you.
-To send him to his death?
To help him save the future.
It has to be you.
We kept these in the archives.
You were wearing them in the hospital
when Torchwood took you.
Good job the moths
haven't got into them.
So I'll be saving
the world in some pyjamas?
How daft is that?
Torchwood 1918 saw you
with Tommy in the hospital
telling him what to do.
I know you,
you're strong enough to do this.
Does Tommy know what happens to him?
-No.
-If he asks me, what do I say?
-Where's Toshiko?
-Still in with Jack.
So, tomorrow morning.
What time is it now?
8:50.
So what do we do till then?
You don't know, do you?
What would you like to do?
The night before we went
over the top, we used to play cards.
Write letters.
Have a drink if anyone had some.
-Well, we could do that.
-Yeah.
But you're not coming with me.
I'm going on my own.
We were just wondering
what Tommy should do tonight.
He can come home with me.
He's not our prisoner,
he doesn't have to stay here.
Does he?
No.
If that's what you both want.
Tomorrow morning, 6:30.
It's time.
You know we can't be here
when it happens.
(ALARM BLARING)
Come on.
Shh!
(MAN SINGING)
We're safe for now.
Are you all right?
Tommy!
Where is she?
In 1918.
GERALD: Tommy,
I think you'd better come with us.
Don't worry.
I'm Gerald and this is Harriet.
We'll look after you.
Torchwood took me.
TOSHIKO: Tommy!
-Tommy!
-Stay here!
I won't do it. I can't go back.
-You've got to.
-No. I know what'll happen.
They'll send me back to the front.
I'll be back in the trenches.
Help me!
You've got to go.
Why me?
You're no better than the generals.
Sitting safely behind the lines,
sending us over the top.
Any one of you lot could go, but you're
not, are you? You're sending me.
-We belong here.
-I'm sorry.
I've been shoved
from pillar to post all my life,
-by the army, by Torchwood.
-Hey, hey, hey.
All this time I've had,
it means nothing.
-Tommy...
-Get off!
-Tommy, get up.
-No!
Leave us alone. Please.
JACK: You've got two minutes.
Listen,
you're a hero.
Do you know that?
Because you stop the time shift
and save everyone.
You save us all.
I can't do it.
We need you.
I don't want to be a hero.
I want to stay here, with you.
(WIND HOWLING AND CRASHING)
GERALD: Hello?
-Tell them.
-Tell us what?
Tell them what to do.
You're the only one
who can stop this. If you don't...
If you don't,
it's the end of everything.
Tommy.
Take me. I'm in there,
in the ward, in 1918.
You have to take me
so I can be here now.
Just take me!
I'll be gone soon.
Remember the rift key. Use it.
You've got to get back into bed
like you've never been away.
Then use the key.
Tommy?
Remember.
It's nearly time.
What are you doing?
You shouldn't be in here.
Go! Go!
Come on!
Tommy, I think you'd better
come with us.
-Why?
-Don't worry.
I'm Gerald and this is Harriet.
We'll look after you.
Who are you?
We're Torchwood.
-Where are we going?
-Somewhere safe. Trust me.
It's all right. Keep going.
Don't look back.
You should be in bed.
It's still warm at least.
Not been gone long.
(ALARM BLARING)
-What's happening?
-I don't know.
The time shift hasn't stopped.
Toshiko, show me the city now!
TOSHIKO:
It's spreading out from the hospital.
What the hell are they?
Chunks of the past
erupting into the present.
They're everywhere.
-What about the rift key?
-Tommy isn't using it.
-Why not?
-I don't know.
Because he's just
gone back to 90 years ago?
Because he's shellshocked?
One of us will have to go back.
Jack, wait! You'll get stuck in 1918.
I've got an idea. The time shifts
are forcing the rift open.
If we are quick,
we can use it to our advantage.
A tiny amount should do.
We know Tommy's exact location in time.
We send an image of you through to him.
-I can go into Tommy's mind.
-As a psychic projection, yes.
If we're lucky.
-And Tommy will be able to see you.
-I can make him use the key.
Let me do it.
He trusts me.
Okay.
-How long have I got?
-Minutes.
You've got one shot, Tosh. That's all.
All right?
(PATIENTS SCREAMING)
Tommy.
-Tommy.
-She's found him.
It's me.
Toshiko.
Who?
I'm here to help you.
-Is this yours?
-No.
Do you know what it is?
Tommy, it's a key.
You have to use it.
-I'm scared.
-It's all right.
That's why I'm here. I'm a coward.
-No, you are not.
-What am I fighting for?
For the future, for me.
Because you're my brave, handsome hero.
Tommy, use the key.
Thank you.
Goodbye.
All right?
He did it.
GWEN: You all right?
Hey...
Thank you.
He trusted me, right to the end.
Because you were strong.
All of this
is still here because of you.
Because of Tommy.
Let's hope we're worth it.
RHYS: I'm from Harwood's. I'm going to
need to arrange to move the lorry.
The police have taken the meat out
of the back of the van.
OWEN: It's definitely alien meat.
-Have you any idea why?
-How would I know?
JACK: We've got to shut the operation
down and identify the alien meat.
You lied! You were at that crash.
-Rhys?
-He must be in on it.
I was hoping maybe I could pick up
from where he left off, boys?
Let's go.
Aliens in Cardiff?
-GWEN: It's amazing.
-Imprisoned, chained and drugged.
Welcome to planet Earth.